Many models now ship with 1 million
tokens of context window, but it's
pretty shocking how little of that is
usable for actual work. All models
suffer from attention degradation, which
means that the more tokens you have in
the context window, the worse the agent
performs. The reason for this is
whenever you add a token to the context
window, the model needs to keep track of
not just that token, but also its
relationships to every other token. So,
here we have five tokens, but 10
attention relationships. If you have
10,000 tokens, then that's 1 million
attention relationships, which means
that at some point the model starts to
perform worse, starts to create more
hallucinations, starts to retrieve
information less well, starts to write
worse code. And so, practically, you can
think of the agent as having a smart
zone and a dumb zone. This isn't a like
immediate drop-off, it slowly sinks
down, and some tasks don't need that
much of a smart zone. So, you can do
some tasks in the dumb zone. But, if you
want to get the most out of the tokens
that you're spending, you want to spend
those tokens in the smart zone, not the
dumb zone. So, the question is, where
does the dumb zone begin? And this is
hotly debated, and it's different per
model, and probably different per task.
However, I think a useful rule of thumb
is around 150,000 tokens. It's pretty
easy to design workflows where you break
down tasks into small chunks, and then
run them in new context windows. And I
found that doing this means I spend
fewer tokens, and I get better results.
This recommendation has moved as well. I
used to think it was around 100K tokens
about 6 months ago. Now, it is going up,
and it will continue to creep up. But,
when you reach the dumb zone, you should
use that as a signal to either clear the
context, compact the context, hand off,
or think on how you can work your
workflow differently to design tasks
that don't need that much context
window. And also, if you're seeing
hallucinations, especially faithfulness
hallucinations, then you're probably in
the dumb zone.